Stanford University I think I mentioned
last time that the horizon of a black
hole is not a place where anything very
dangerous is happening a place for
anything very traumatic what happened to
somebody who fell in in fact if you take
a big black hole now how big let's say
really big really big black hole what
would you find if you fell through the
horizon of the black hole the answer is
you were fine fine nothing there it
would look exactly like flat space or
almost exactly like flat space if the
horizon was big enough and it would just
look like empty space well that's a
little odd because the mathematics that
we wrote down looks like it does have
something striking going on at the
horizon and tonight I want to resolve
that there's a little bit of mathematics
the mathematics is about at the edge of
what I do in this class it's not
terribly hard but we're going to follow
through and unravel what happens very
what the horizon of the black hole is
really like what's going on there all
right so let's write down the metric of
the black hole
that's the beginning always for the
starting with the starting point for
black holes is to write down a metric I
usually write D tau squared where tau
stands for proper time I'm going to use
the other convention the other
convention is just to change the sign of
the whole thing and call it proper
distance I'll explain in a moment proper
distance squared is just the negative of
the proper time between two points I'm
just doing that partly for variety
partly because it will keep me saying
because I know all of these formulas in
this form remember that what we wrote
for the tau squared was just something
involving DT squared all right DT
squared and flat space in fact it was
just the T squared minus the x squared
plus dy squared plus DZ squared that was
the tau squared notice that it's
positive
if DT is bigger than D tau so if along a
trajectory the time difference is bigger
than the space difference for example if
the object was standing perfectly still
in space then the X would be absolutely
zero we've defined the proper time the
tau squared so that it would be problem
positive so that the square of it would
be positive but supposing we were
studying a space like distance the
distance between two points at a fixed
time then with the original definition
this would be negative and when we took
the square root of it we would say that
the distance between these two points is
imaginary well we're going to get stuck
one way or another if we define the
invariant distance so that the square of
it is positive for time like things then
it's going to be negative for space like
things and vice versa so what people do
is to use two different conventions just
whenever you don't like you're convinced
you change the sign well now's a time
that I don't like my convention so I'm
going to change the sign and define the
s squared what does s stand for spatial
distance rather than time distance but
it's just the negative of the proper
time or the square of the proper time
it's not a big deal but let's write down
the metric of a Schwarzschild black hole
in this notation it's one minus two mg
over R sorry only doing it my area the
desk where it has a minus and then a
plus we change the sign from the proper
time
that's the spatial interval okay the
opposite a minus here DT squared and
then you remember what goes here one
over one minus two mg over R D R squared
and then another piece here which I'm
going to ignore this had to do with the
angles on the sky those are squared
times something I think I called the
Omega squared but let's ignore it for
now let's not worry about angular
distance on the sky let's just worry
about time and radial distance all right
so this plus a bit more here when you're
far from the black hole that means when
R is large large compared what's to mg
called
the Schwarzschild radius it's the
Schwarzschild radius of the black hole
to mg if I were to put in speeds of
light it would be two mg over C squared
so right now C is equal to 1 to M G is
the Schwarzschild radius and if you're
far away from the black hole are being
much bigger than the Schwarzschild
radius then this is negligible this is
negligible and it's just the T squared
minus R minus DT squared plus the R
squared exactly as it would be in flat
space plus a bit more as you get close
the black hole you come to the point
where R is approximately 2 mg in other
words a distance more or less the same
as the Schwarzschild radius and then
something rather dramatic happens to
these coefficients this one becomes zero
and this one the in the denominator it
gets to be zero but a zero in the
denominator means something's infinite
sure sounds like something unusual is
happening all right let me show you
exactly what's happening there and it's
a great big nothing nothing is happening
there it's an artifact of the chord of
the choice of coordinates so I'm going
to show you some examples and then we'll
work out in detail what's happening at
the horizon of the black hole um over
here I want to discuss coordinates and
for the moment now I'm only talking
about ordinary Cartesian coordinates on
the plane on the blackboard let's call
them Y and X later on the vertical axis
will become the time axis but for now
the vertical axis is just the y axis all
right now what's the metric of the XY
plane that's pretty easy that's just the
s squared is equal to the x squared plus
dy squared and nothing takes place
especially interesting at the origin or
anyplace else now let's go to polar
coordinates polar coordinates means we
characterize a point by a distance which
I won't call R because I don't want to
confuse it with this R over here it's a
different thing let's call it ro the
Greek letter Rho which is sort of like R
and what's the other variable theta
angle
okay first of all what is X in terms of
Rho and theta we'll just drop a
perpendicular X is equal to Rho times
cosine of theta right that's the
definition of cosine and Y is Rho sine
theta everybody agree okay good now what
about the metric in terms of Rho and
theta supposing we start at this point
over here and we make a little excursion
over to here a little differential
displacement and that little bit of
differential displacement corresponds to
changing are a certain amount let's pick
the red red line here is dr that's dr
and the other red line here how long is
that this distance here is just dr but
what about the distance perpendicular to
it
visit the theta Rho D theta Rho D theta
the further away you are the bigger a
given D theta corresponds to so that's
Rho D theta so now can you write down
what the metric is so you can D s
squared is equal to D R squared D Rho
squared sorry this is D Rho D Rho not
they are though you will use with save
offer over there D Rho D Rho squared
plus Rho squared D theta squared that's
the metric in polar coordinates notice
it has a funny property the funny
property nothing gets infinite in this
metric but no this is a funny property
that the coefficient of the D theta
becomes zero at Rho equals zero and
moving in theta you don't get anywhere
you don't move
even if you move and theta oh why not
well because she's just not moving very
much when you move around theta at the
origin here's a situation also this
becomes zero and it looks like when T
changes nothing is happening if this is
zero we'll see we'll see as we go along
that they're very very similar kinds of
things
okay everybody understand that that's
just good old polar coordinates but now
let's go to Minkowski space the space
time of special relativity
instead of using Y for the vertical axis
we will now use let's call it capital T
I'm not going to call it small T I'm
going to call it capital T and the
horizontal axis I will call X again all
right so T is replacing Y now and what's
the metric now the metric now is the S
squared is equal to minus DT squared
plus the x squared this is just
two-dimensional now we don't need the
other dimensions for this argument for
to explain what's happening here just
minus DT squared plus DX squared the
minus is there for special relativity
okay so that's our metric it looks sort
of like this but only a sign change
either I'm going to now introduce
polar coordinates but they called
hyperbolic polar coordinates let's just
draw in here the light cones these are
the light cones of light rays move along
the go through the origin we're going to
introduce again a radial variable or a
Rho which measures distance from the
origin but not ordinary distance proper
distance from the origin and a time
variable that I'm going to call Omega
here's the relationship here's the
definitions X I go up to the top where X
equals Rho cosine theta we're going to
replace that by x equals Rho hyperbolic
cosine theta but not theta we'll call it
Omega it's a standard terminology for a
hyperbolic angle I'm going to tell you
more about hyperbolic angles as we go
along if you're forgotten but the but
let's just write down the equations on
the blackboard but this isn't right I
left out something what I leave out Rho
completely parallel to what I've written
up there and T is equal to Rho times the
hyperbolic sine of Omega all right now
what a hyperbolic sine and cosine will
whatever they are let's come back to
cosine and sine cosine squared plus sine
squared equals 1 that's a statement of
basically Pythagorean theorem that this
side squared plus that side squared is
that side squared is the hypotenuse
squared for a unit triangle how about
for this hyperbolic guys what's the
equation for them hache squared Omega
minus sin squared Omega equals 1 all
right that's one thing and let me tell
you what what costume cinch mean from
the diagram up above we can think of
this by first drawing a circle by first
drawing our unit circle draw our unit
circle draw the angle theta and then X
is given in terms of cosine for unit
circle it's just X is equal to cosine Y
is equal to sine we do the same thing
except not with a circle but with a
hyperbola we take the hyperbola let's
okay let's let's raise this up let's
take the hyperbola naught x squared plus
y squared equals 1 but x squared minus T
squared equals 1 so take the hyperbola x
squared minus T squared equals 1 that
looks like this
that's a hyperbola that looks like this
and now take a point on that unit
hyperbola at any point draw the same
kind of right triangle that we drew for
the for the circle take a point drop the
perpendicular drop a perpendicular this
side here is hyperbolic sine of the
angle and this side here is hyperbolic
cosine so everything is exactly the same
except for a sign change and that sign
change manifests itself and a sign
change in the relation between cosines
and sines okay now we have x equals Rho
cos Omega T equals Rho since Omega
almost the same as the equation for x
and y up there let's guess what the
metric looks like here it is DS squared
which is just where is it did I write it
here it is the S squared is minus DT
squared plus DX squared is this easy to
work out is equal to Rho squared the
Omega squared with a minus sign and with
a plus sign
d Rho squared let's just compare it go
up to the metric over here the S squared
is Rho squared plus Rho squared 0
squared plus Rho squared D theta squared
the Rho squared same thing and instead
of Rho squared D theta squared we have a
minus sign
Rho squared the Omega squared Omega is
like theta but there is a big difference
between Omega and theta theta is a
periodic variable it goes around on a
circle it goes from 0 to 2 pi and it
never gets bigger than 2 pi then of
course it jumps back to 0 again Omega
goes from minus infinity way down here
goes up to here becomes 0 at this point
and then goes up the plus infinity so
hyperbolic angles unlike ordinary angles
go from minus infinity to infinity and
of course you can see that what happens
what happens when Omega gets very large
let's think about for a moment what
happens when Omega gets very very large
what happens to hyperbolic cosine of
Omega it's very easy just look at this
picture it gets big fact it gets big
exponentially fast with Omega so this
gets very big all right what about cinch
cinch is another way of talking about
hyperbolic sine what happens to it does
it get big or small no it's big yeah how
do I know if this gets very big and the
difference between cosh and cinch is
only a tiny number 1 then cinch better
get as big as cosh apart from the
difference once or if if cost is 100
billion then cinch also has to be a
hundred billion - a little tiny bit so
when Omega gets large cost and cinch
become very close to being equal to each
other all right that means when you go
way out at large hyperbolic angle you're
way out here way up on this light cone
here where T and X are almost equal to
each other way out here on this
hyperboloid so way out in this
hyperboloid is where Omega gets large
Omega goes to infinity way out on the
hyperbola and way down here it goes to
minus and today we're going to see that
Omega is a kind
time variable if it wasn't clear already
we're going to see that Omega is a kind
of time variable that keeps time but it
keeps time in this angular kind of way I
move along these hyperboloids
hyperbolas Omega is a kind of time Rho
is a kind of distance okay and that's
the metric the S squared is minus Rho
squared the Omega squared plus 2i we
haven't worked this out but it follows
in a very similar manner to the way that
it did up there
okay so here's something let's keep this
in mind I want you to remember this
formula in fact I'm not even going to
trust you to remember it we're going to
leave it on the blackboard and we're
going to come back to the short chilled
metric let's come back to the
Schwarzschild metric oh let me just say
it now this metric with this peculiar
Rho dependence here what space is it
what spacetime is it it's just flat
Minkowski space with nothing going on
special anywheres on it it's just we've
chosen to write it in polar coordinates
where the coordinate system has
something funny going on at the origin
but there's nothing funny physically
going on there it's just a coordinate
gimmick okay what we want the show now
is that this metric close to the horizon
is basically like this it takes a couple
of steps I wish I could do this all in
one quick step but it takes a couple of
steps but they're not hard
they're just them on the edge of what I
like doing on the blackboard okay
let's rewrite the metric once let's
multiply let's write this as R minus two
mg over R I just written one as R over R
DT squared minus and this is plus
r / r minus two mg times the r-squared
this coefficient and this one are
inverse to each other
I've done nothing I've simply rewritten
it in a form which a little neater ok
now what I'm interested in is the black
hole very near the horizon
in other words are very close to 2 mg
what we want to do is we want to zoom in
on R equals to mg and sort of expand out
and see what's going on there by making
some approximations but approximations
which are highly accurate right at R
equals to mg and the approximation
approximation we're going to make is in
the denominator here we're not going to
be moving much here's let's suppose here
is here is R equals 2 and this is our R
axis here is 2 mg we're going to only be
moving a little bit just to explore the
very very neighborhood of this point so
we're going to make little excursions
away from this point but all is not
going to change much so I'm going to
replace R by 2 mg should I do the same
over here now that's not a good idea
because notice what happens when you
move are a little bit near here
this thing can change sign so we better
keep it the way it is better not fool
around with it the two mg or in the
denominator here that doesn't do
anything very interesting as you move
are a little bit if 2 mg is a kilometer
and you move a centimeter to mg only
changes a tiny bit of kilometer plus or
minus a centimeter but R minus two mg it
flew
sign that's dangerous so let's keep this
just the way it is
all right likewise here I've just turned
this thing over and put it here so
that's the first step to make a little
bit of an approximation that's the first
step
haven't done much now the next step is
to look at this over here and say look
it's just B Rho squared over here I'm
going to do a trick I'm going to change
variables I'm going to change
coordinates from R to a new coordinate
which I'll call Rho in such a way that
this whole thing here and we'll see how
to do this in a moment in such a way
that this whole thing here is just
called D Rho squared now how can I do
that how can I say that the R minus two
mg won't or whatever it is here oh sorry
sorry this should be 2 mg here right -
mg 2 mg in the numerator just how can I
do that well I haven't told you what Rho
is yet so until I tell you what Rho is
there's no contradiction it just may be
that Rho is related to our in such a way
that this makes sense so let's see if we
can figure out what the relationship
between Rho and ours that's the first
step which is dealing with this term
here
well it says that the Rho squared must
be the same which is another word for
equals equals to mg over R minus two mg
the R squared let me take the square
root of both sides square root square
root square root this is an equation
that determines Rho in terms of r how do
I find grow in terms of r from an
equation like this you'll integrate both
sides of the equation alright so what do
you get on the left hand side if you
integrate the left hand side row
what are we getting the right hand side
that's a little harder huh not too much
harder let's take out hmm
take out the fact that 2mg and now this
becomes dr over square root of r minus
two mg this piece is not that's just a
constant anybody smart enough to do that
integral takes me about ten minutes I'm
going to wait for somebody else
the grill over here is 2 times R square
root of R minus two mg that's the
integral of this so let's let's write
the correct equation Rho is equal to
square root of 2mg
times another factor of 2 that makes
this 8 times square root of R minus two
mg ok if you don't believe it
differentiate Rho with respect to R and
check this is the same equation as
saying that the Rho by dr is equal to 2
mg over R minus two mg is the solution
differentiate with respect to R and
reproduce that that's an exercise for
you alright so now we found what Rho has
to be in order that we can take this
whole mess here and just write D Rho
squared
isn't that nice we now don't have to
worry about any factors multiplying this
but it may be getting a little
complicated because we're going to
really want to rewrite everything in
terms of Rho we're changing variables
and here are appears nice and simply
right well it's not so bad
look at this R minus two mg times
something is equal to Rho squared square
this equation let's square it
I won't let's see maybe I should write
robust yeah Rho squared is equal to 8 M
G times R minus two M G Holy Smoke I now
know what R minus two mg is it's just a
Rho squared over 8 mg that wasn't so bad
and now we can write the metric are
minus two mg let's even let's even go a
little further let's divide by another
two mg here because that's what we're
going to need and we're going to get 16
M Squared G squared 16 M Squared G
squared as I said a little bit tedious
but not too bad okay so let's see what
we have here we have roast - Rho squared
DT squared divided by 16 M squared G
squared plus this well take a look at
this first look at this and then look at
this they're not the same but they're
fairly close you have a D Rho squared
and you have a Rho squared times a DT
squared but you'll have this nuisance 16
M squared G squared down stairs right
that doesn't appear over here well it's
really easy to get rid of it how do you
do it now we say that we change we've
changed the our variable to Rho now
we're going to change the T variable to
Omega I don't think we need what's in
the bottom here done all of that now I
just say that T over 4 M G call that
Omega the T squared of a 16 M squared G
squared is the Omega squared it's just a
change of variables by rescaling the
time by this factor for M G and what do
we get then we get that this is equal a
minus Rho squared the Omega squared plus
D Rho squared
in other words we get exactly flat space
in hyperbolic polar coordinates now it
wasn't exactly because we didn't make a
slight approximation but it's an
approximation which was essentially
exact at R equals to mg we replaced an R
by a to M G here and r by a to M G here
but that's okay because we're only
moving R by a tiny amount away from two
mg so what are we seeing we've seen that
to a high approximation the region near
the horizon near R equals to mg has a
metric where is it well it has a metric
which is just the metric of flat space
this is good enough to tell us that
there's nothing fancy going on at the
horizon nothing dramatic no forces
become infinite nothing traumatic
happens to somebody who finds himself
there it's just a change of coordinates
mmm three squares along
put the equation back on the board
you know the you expect that if first
faulty runs was integrate row won't have
radical changes but if if if RS is
slightly larger citizen to the
Schwarzschild radius it's positive
if is equal row is 0 and it is negative
growing I it is a imaginary number the
is just like an odd integral that have
any effect well we just reproduce what's
here same things the same thing no yeah
mm-hmm okay let's um remind ourselves
what these coordinates look like the
drawn over here but let me redraw them
the simply Minkowski space light-cone an
origin a hyperbolic angle it measures
time so to speak along there and but
really when we put it all together it's
just flat space and some funny
coordinates
what's this point right over here in
terms of our that point is of course row
equals zero that point is of course row
equals zero but what is Rho equals zero
row equals zero is R equals two mg so
you can imagine somebody coming in from
far away is far away from the black hole
moving in moving in moving in moving in
and getting to that point and that point
is the horizon of the black hole that's
where the horizon is right at that point
now we can start to understand a little
better our it's a little weird we start
with a black hole which looks like a
well those look like far from the black
hole it looks just like flat space close
to the horizon it also looks like flat
space but in a very very different way
the time up there becomes the hyperbolic
angle times 4 mg so it's a rather odd
transformation but the main point here
is that nothing special is going on at
this horizon over here ok any questions
about this ok let's talk about where the
horizon is now somebody who is outside
the horizon is at an R which is larger
than 2 mg what does that mean in terms
of Rho it means at a positive value of
Rho squared it means out here remember
the hyperbolas are lines of constant Rho
is Rho equal 1 value is Rho equals
another value is a bigger value of Rho
and so forth outside the black hole is
to the right of this pair of lines out
that's outside the black hole if you're
outside the black hole let's suppose
over here and you want to send a message
which will continue to move outward you
can send the message out and that
message will eventually pass any one of
these hyperbolas that message a light
ray between the light ray out and that
light ray will cross any one of these
hyperbolas so if we imagine a person
station that each one of these
hyperbolas that we
station that value of our elite value of
our we have another guy the standing
still which means they're on a fixed our
trajectory which means a fixed road
trajectory somebody in here sends a
message can they get a message to
somebody far out yes they can get a
message to anybody no matter how far out
because this message will eventually
cross everyone is a Kerberos is one our
friend forever look predict your proper
time or particular distance is what I
prefer when our purple ax is a given
proper distance from the horizon yeah
about distance distance you are yeah
yeah right the H hyperbola is a given
distance from right remember there's a
coordinate transformation between R and
Rho where is it we had it written down
somewhere if it is let's let's get it
back again
oh I lost something but them it's got a
square root and then another square root
of 8 mg yeah okay as long as R is bigger
than 2 mg this square root is positive
if the square root is positive Rho
squared is positive and for each value
of Rho there's one value of R and for
each value of R you can define one value
of Rho let's not worry about negative
values for the square root all right
each value of Rho comes with a value of
R so a given value of R is on one of
these hyperboloids on one of these row
lines ok so that's a that's the facts
for outside the black hole if somebody
is stationed outside the black hole they
can send the message to anybody else no
matter how far out they are ya know
no obstruction if you're outside the
horizon to communicating with anybody
else
on the top left understand there's a
third equation camp on the second now
pork the rack that was not a question
state again real estate seems like the
third equation doesn't follow on the
second very equation 1 2 3 here from
idiot yeah for the first terms just got
the comment on the right hand side are
very close to two energies okay I put
our beer then to the ball okay
as I said this was the approximation
that we made which is an accurate
approximation and is more and more
accurate as R becomes closer and closer
to 2 mg okay
um where are we yeah I know what about a
few over here can you send the message
Alka here remember light moves on
45-degree trajectories light moves on
light cones if somebody is over here can
they send a message out to the outside
the outside meaning anywhere is out
beyond this light cone no they can't so
the world sort of divides into the place
where you can send the message out
beyond this like home and all the way
you can send messages out to people at
positive values of r and those places
where you can't that's the definition of
a horizon in fact this whole like light
like line is the horizon if you find if
you fall through here that is let's now
imagine ah two friends Alice and Bob all
right Bob insists on staying outside the
black hole but and he's going to stay at
a fixed distance from the black hole so
there he is he's going along on his
trajectory and Alice decides to fall
past that point once Alice passes this
point over here she can no longer send a
message to Bob Bob can't see her if he
can't get a light ray from her he can't
see her he can't get a message from her
Canales see Bob yeah no problem
is Alice over here oops
Alice looks back on her light-cone and
sees Bob so there's an asymmetry Alice
can see Bob but Bob can't see Alice
Alice has passed the horizon of the
black hole but does anything happen at
that point no nothing special at this
point this was just good old flat space
and nothing special happened yeah that's
because the photons are coming from Bob
toward Alice so that she can see him
yeah if she jumps through the horizon is
in hip-deep to see your own feet because
she sees her feet as she passes through
yeah well if she's outside and her feet
pass yeah yeah she can't see her own
feet while she's outside but how long
does she stay outside
not very long as a matter of fact you
can't see your feet right at this
instant you can only see your feet after
this little time for light to get to
your eye from your feet by that time
Alice's eyes there's a continuous view
of her feet as she falls through there's
like a little blip where no no nothing
at all nothing at all she's just she's
doing what she always does this is not a
special place now should her head after
her feet pass through the horizon should
her head decide oh no I am NOT going to
pass through the horizon then her head
will never see her feet
that's if she is going to move along one
of these trajectory and her feet move
into here we don't want this is not a
good thing this is not a good thing and
then our feet the yeah so as long as you
don't do anything violent what you see
when you fall into the black hole is
what you would have seen if you hadn't
fallen into a black hole what somebody
sees of you if that somebody is
stationary with respect to the are
coordinates that's a different story
so let's see what let's see what a
person stationary let's put them on one
of these trajectories is there anything
unusual about one of these trajectories
they're curved
what does it mean that they're curved
that they're accelerated
they're accelerating should this be a
surprise that to stay out of the black
hole
somebody has to accelerate are you
accelerating now yep at least relative
you're accelerating relative to a freely
falling frame right exactly right so to
stay out of the black hole it's true
that Bob has to accelerate maybe he has
to have a rocket I would if I didn't
have the floor here to support me I
would have to have a jet pack to keep
from falling down right okay so nothing
nothing terribly unusual ah no the
further away you get the less sticks the
less intense the acceleration has to be
but it is true that Bob has to
accelerate to stay outside he lets go of
Alice lets go of Alice and Alice falls
into the black hole
she he's got the jet pack she lets go of
her hand and she falls in let's say over
here she doesn't accelerate so she moves
on a straight line so there is an
asymmetry there's a basic physical
asymmetry that the bob has the jet pack
on Alice doesn't and Alice falls behind
in the horizon over here she can
continue to see Bob nothing special
happens Bob loses track of her cannot
see her so let's see what Bob can see
his Bob what Bob can see is light coming
to him light comes to him along these
light cones so when he's over here he
sees Alice over here Alice is waving to
him over here you go a little bit
further he sees Alice over here go a
little bit further he sees Alice over
here what happens asymptotically as he
looks back from his
at increasing Omega his Omega is getting
larger and larger and larger and he's
looking back does he ever see Alice fall
through the black hole horizon no
ultimately asymptotically when Bob looks
from the arbitrary future he simply sees
Alice getting closer and closer and
closer to the horizon but never crossing
it so from Bob's perspective Alice does
not cross the horizon she just gets
closer and closer and closer to the
horizon sort of getting pancaked onto it
if you like it's not just her nose that
gets flattened for the horizon the back
of her head does too here's her nose
here's the back of her head following
her in and they both he looks back and
he sees them both extremely close to the
horizon so he sees asymptotically they
get closer and closer but never quite
falling through that horizon here what
about Alice does she say that she find
any obstruction at this point no no
obstruction at all
she just sails through happily nothing
happens to her so there's already just
at this level even not even from black
holes just thinking about accelerated
observers who stay outside of this
trajectory outside of his light cone
here there's already a bit of a tension
an observer who moves on a trajectory
like this on a hyperbola ah has a set of
observations that include among them
that Alice Falls toward the horizon but
never sees her go through the horizon
yes indeed well then we have to worry
about quantum mechanics
remember plunk length has h-bar in it
and we cannot answer that question
without without some quantum mechanics
now we've already done a little bit of
quantum mechanics about black holes
they're very elementary we derived the
entropy and some other things about the
black hole by saying we fill it up with
photons if you remember what we did
there was an H in the formula so we've
already started to think about the
quantum mechanics of black holes but
from a different perspective if you look
at Rosa pulsar
take a big R and Hart get smaller it'll
go along the exercise until it hits that
passing point
or equality let's let's draw the
different here let's draw a first R
equals big R little R little R here
equals 1 here's R equals 1 that could be
one kilometer everywhere is along there
now let's draw sorry this is big R
little R little R one kilometer from the
horizon so R is bigger than 2 mg 2 mg
plus a kilometer to mg plus a kilometer
is to mg plus half a kilometer is to mg
plus a quarter of a kilometer is to mg
plus 1/8 of a kilometer right on here oh
then it's in here somewheres but we
don't want to do we don't want to go
there yet but the moment we don't want
to go there so Rho the integral the it
basically takes right angle yeah yeah
does that mean it's not you can't take
its derivative it's right angles well
something something singular happens at
that point but it's not the main thing
is it's not a physical phenomenon that
takes place it's a change of coordinates
it's a funny glitch in the coordinates
it will come to it
we'll talk about what's behind here and
how you think about it in coordinates
but for the time being we have
everything we want just by drawing these
is omega proper time in the accelerated
reference almost almost what is a proper
time is rho times omega okay remember
the metric for where is it the metric
for omega is Rho squared the Omega
squared right so that means Rho along
one of these trajectories fixed row for
fixed row row times D Omega is proper
time along there okay so it's almost its
proper time but with the Rho scaled out
it's the same thing as talking about
circles is angular proper distance along
the circle well not quite
it's proper distance except you have to
multiply by by the radius to make the
proper distance okay all right that's
that's the properties of a black hole
horizon and the bottom line is the
properties or a black hole horizon are
boring well they're boring to somebody
who falls through but they're kind of
interesting to somebody who stays
outside somebody who stays outside sees
their friend do some weird things see
some slowdown sees them get flattened
against this horizon and so there's a
kind of tension there but so far no
paradox just the tension in the
description of things you know at this
point you could ask well does Alice
really fall through what doesn't she
really fall through well what's the
answer the answer is it's a question a
point of view I mean from from Bob's
point of view no she doesn't
the injury's ball can only see finitely
for analysis future y/o finitely for
analysis future that's correct well
that's what that's what alice would say
bob says i see how forever and ever she
just gets slower and slower and duller
and duller maybe subconscious adjustment
to see our feet as needing to comment on
their eyes so we have to say
unconscious you know get unconscious
crossing the metaphysics the question of
measurement or observation right so what
future doesn't have sight lines into
Alice's entire future Bob will simply
say what I see is Alice approaching the
horizon asymptotically and never passing
it that's what he'll say now you can
tell him a story while Alice really fell
through blah blah blah he was good he
won't see her age he won't see her age
she know she just everything slows down
everything slows down and she but it's
not a profitable question to ask does
this or that really happen it is a
proper profitable question to ask what
what observations and what measurements
and correlation of data Bob will do as a
physicist or as whatever he is and we
could ask what kind of things Alice
detects and observes and at all they'll
see fog like zipping away
I think so ha recently yeah that's right
Alice sees but Alice sees Bob's a boy
can you say to forget about that this
isn't specific Platt hold Annie I think
he said telling this this isn't specific
black hole this drama is right this this
particular phenomena will be just for a
uniformly accelerated observer if we had
an observer riding on a rocket that had
enough fuel to allow it to to accelerate
indefinitely moving away then that
observer on that rocket would say for
all practical purposes there was an end
to the world could not see beyond it and
could see nothing fall through it so he
would say there is a horizon it's called
an acceleration horizon but but it's not
physically different in the black hole
horizon right remember what Einstein
taught us he said if you want to
understand gravity first understand
acceleration if you want to understand
how phenomena happen in a gravitational
field first understand how they happen
in a uniformly accelerated frame of
reference well what we've learned is
that in a uniformly accelerated frame of
reference and that's what this is the
sequence of lines here there is an
acceleration horizon so Einstein could
have invented the idea of a horizon
before there was any notion of a black
hole and then if he was smart enough if
he was a smart as Einstein he would have
said well this probably means that
there's some gravitational context which
in which these horizons show up Einstein
incidentally did not believe in black
holes
he thought they violated something
okay now I want to turn back before we
do we'll take a break but I want to turn
back to the discussion that we started
last time about temperature entropy a
little bit and the thermodynamic
properties of black holes that they have
because they do have a temperature and
so local Oh will do that after a seven
minute break let's see maybe I'll get
away with one blackboard we'll see let
me put on my thermodynamic app now heat
what we did last time is we imagine
building up the black hole by dropping
little drops in the same way we would
drop drops into the bathtub and fill it
up and try to see how many drops it
takes to fill it to a certain level in
the black hole case there was how many
bits or how many photons each carrying
one bit of information do we have to put
in to create a black hole of the given
size and what we discovered is that each
bit that we drop in increases the area
of the horizon by one plunk length when
I say one thick one with a grain of salt
we didn't do these real calculation
which gives us a factor of 1/4 why a
factor of 1/4 well what it probably
means by what it does mean is that
whoever invented the idea of the Planck
length and it was plunk simply got it
wrong by a factor of four he should have
defined it to be four times as big or
one-fourth I forget but and then we
wouldn't have this nuisance for hanging
around after all was purely a historical
time and plunk knew nothing whatever
about black holes horizons information
and black holes and so forth so we just
did some dimensional and
analysis of his a length if he would
have defined it as four times or two
times different than forward in the bin
math okay one of the things we did was
to calculate the change in energy if we
drop in one bit again remember what a
bit means a bit means a photon whose
wavelength is comparable to this whole
size of the black hole how much does the
energy change now I also told you last
time that the definition of temperature
let's just go back a step
temperature seems like a naive and naive
meaning to say an easily understood
concept you feel it with your fingers on
the table here you measure it with
thermometers we all know what it means
but in fact it's an extremely subtle and
somewhat derived concept entropy is an
extremely confusing thing when people go
to learn thermodynamics for the first
time entropy is thrown at them into what
the hell is that um in fact entropy is
very very basic and in some sense simple
energy and entropy are really the basis
for thermodynamics or for statistical
mechanics temperature is a derived
concept what is entropy well whatever it
is it comes in bits and has to do with
information it has to do with yes/no
questions energy let's suppose we all
knew what energy was which I suspect
most of us have some idea so we have
entropy and energy the definition of
temperature is simply the energy that's
liberated are the energy change in a
system when you add one bit of
information to it the minimum change of
energy when you add one bit
I say minimum the the the nice analogue
is the computer you want to erase a bit
of information from your computer that
bit of information
to go someplace it can't disappear it
goes on for the atmosphere and it
necessarily adds a certain amount of
energy to the atmosphere of course if
you are sloppy and erasing the bit you
know you do you do it with a
sledgehammer your you can add a lot more
energy to the atmosphere than that but
if you're very careful of course you'll
also be adding more bits of information
whether they're very careful to just
erase that bit minimal way then the
minimum and energy that you have to add
to the atmosphere in that case is called
the temperature the energy necessary to
change the entropy by one unit okay so
you keep that definition in the back of
your head of what the temperature is
it's energy needed to change or energy
liberated when you add one bit to a
system okay let's go back now and say
here we have our black hole we're going
to throw in a photon whose wavelength is
comparable to the size of the black hole
look and let's calculate the change in
energy well all we have to know is how
much energy one photon of a wavelength
here's the wavelength the wavelength is
comparable to the Schwarzschild radius
let's call it R it's equal to twice the
mass times G that's also the wavelength
of the photon it looks to me like my
wavelength is a little bit long let's
shorten it up a little bit something
like that but so what's the energy of a
photon of wavelength lambda lambda is
the usual definition of the wavelength
usual symbol for it what's the energy of
it the energy of it is Planck's constant
divided by lambda and now there's a
speed of light and the speed of light is
in the numerator for the moment I'm
going to keep the constants later on
today tonight we're going to throw away
the constants or let's throw them away
but we'll work in units in which they
are equal to one I'll just
I get bored carrying them around but
let's keep them for a time being
alright H times C divided by lambda
let's just check if it makes sense the
energy of a photon when plunks constant
is goes to zero gets smaller and smaller
that makes sense a single photon has a
tiny bit of energy why does it have a
tiny bit of energy because Planck's
constant is so small it's also true
there's the wavelength gets long the
energy of a photon goes down long
wavelength photons have low energy short
wavelength photons have high energy and
the speed of light you can just check
that it's really got to be there okay
that's the energy that you add when you
add one photon which carries one bit
well the energy to add one bit that's
the temperature so this must be the
temperature of the black hole and it is
when I say it's the temperature I mean
within a factor of maybe these tools and
PI's because we're not keeping track of
detail the numerical constants I'll tell
you the numerical constants later if you
want okay
the temperature is HC over lambda oh
since I'm keeping track for the moment
for the moment since I'm keeping track
of constants I've left something out of
here C squared speed of light squared
yeah all right so that's the temperature
but remember that lambda is supposed to
be chosen equal to the size of the black
hole so let's put that in either R or H
C over twice mg and another C squared in
the numerator so Planck's constant times
C cubed and we can't trust this factor
of 2 the factor of 2 is not trustworthy
I'll tell you what the right answer is
in a minute
HC cubed divided by the mass times G
notice one curious thing
that as the mass gets bigger and bigger
Oh several things first thing H appears
there that means that the temperature of
the black hole is a quantum effect it
would be zero if H bar of Planck's
constant was zero so it's a thing which
only happens because Planck's constant
is not zero it's another way of saying
it's there because of quantum mechanics
C cubed well it's there for dimensional
reasons the mass is in the denominator
that's interesting the bigger the mass
of the black hole the colder it is now
that's a little bit odd for the
following reason mass is energy e equals
mc-squared
so energy and mass are the same thing
you're used to the idea when you add
energy to something it gets hotter a
black hole gets cooler when you add
energy to it bigger its mass the cooler
it is that's got an odd consequence will
come to that odd consequence in a moment
but let's just keep track of it this is
the temperature of the black hole I'll
give you the right formula now if I
write it in terms of H bar then I know
the answer and it's 8 pi that's the
actual correct answer H bar the time C
cubed divided by 8 pi times mass times R
times Newton's constant okay first
question how hot is a real solar mass
black hole so for that we would stick in
a mass come on what's the mass of a
solar mass 10 to the 10th of 30th
kilograms or something so the big number
downstairs G is a small number C cubed
is huge and H bar is teeny teeny teeny
so some competition of big numbers and
small numbers but the final answer is
that this is a small number this is but
not that small well it's small
this is about for a solar mass black
hole for a black hole of stellar mass
this is about 10 to the minus 8 Kelvin
so it's colder than anything let's see
is it colder than anything in there
I think people talk about getting down
to nano kelvins for some reasons or
other so there may be things in
laboratories are actually colder than
this but this is damn cold ok it's so
cold that it's much much colder than
empty space even in the remotest regions
of the universe where they're far far
from any stars or anything else we know
that the temperature of empty space to
the extent that empty space that space
is empty
ordinary empty space is about 3 degrees
Kelvin that's their microwave background
and so the black hole is cold this this
black hole is colder than anything in
empty space that means even if you had
such a black hole which there was
nothing else around to fall into it even
if you managed to create a black hole in
otherwise completely empty space the
empty space around it would be hotter
than it is what happens when you take a
cold object and put it in a hopper and a
hot bath heat flows from the cold object
from the warm region to the cold region
another way of saying it is the black
hole simply swallows up the microwave
radiation that just sucks it in but you
can also just think of it as the flow of
heat from warm to cold okay what happens
now what happens if if I'm in outer
space that I'm cold but somebody brings
a heater and warms me up I get warmer
right if I if I absorb some heat now
let's think about what happens to the
black hole the black hole absorbs some
heat from its surroundings what happens
to its mass if it's absorbed some heat
it increases its energy increases but
then what happens to its temperature it
goes down it gets even colder it gets
even colder what happens when it gets
even colder it even becomes more
efficient than absorbing heat but it
absorbs heat that gets colder all right
catch-22 it the more it absorbs heat the
colder it gets but let's imagine that we
had a black hole I don't know where it
came from which happens to be a little
bit warmer than the surroundings which
way does the heat go he goes from the
black hole into the atmosphere the black
hole loses mass what happens when it
loses mass it gets hotter so it's a
runaway situation and for black holes
cooler than its environment it will
absorb energy and get colder if the
black hole is warmer than its
environment it will give off energy and
get hotter and it will just run away as
its as its running away of course and
getting hotter its gets mass is getting
smaller and smaller sort of an explosive
situation its mass gets smaller and
smaller it gets hotter and hotter and
eventually gets so hot that it just
explodes if that's if it runs in that
direction so a black hole in thermal
equilibrium with its environment is
unstable even if it had exactly the same
temperature as its environment a
fluctuation could happen by accident
just by random fluctuation it might
absorb a little bit of extra energy if
it did so it would get colder if it got
colder it would be more of an absorber
and it would run away or it might
accidentally give off a little more
extra energy in which case we get hotter
and then give off yet more so in that
sense black holes or understand they
might think that means they're
unphysical there are other systems in
nature which have this property
in fact any system that's held together
by gravity a star stars when they what
happens to a star when it gives off
energy is you it shrinks that's right it
collapses when it gives off energy a try
it thinks that a lot of cool alright so
I'm going to cool because it's because
it thinks it's going to cool that it
thinks it has less pressure the stars
don't think but I need a but you know
alright so are things so less pressure
to haul the stuff out because it has
less precious stuff starts to fall in
what happens when it falls in roughly
speaking you can just imagine that the
gas and stuff in that star is getting
squeezed what happens when you squeeze
it it's hotter yeah so a star is an
example of a system held together by
gravity which when it when it gives off
energy gets hotter a star in thermal
equilibrium with its environment now
thermal equilibrium with its environment
would mean that the environment would
have to have the temperature of the star
so we're not talking about the real
universe but if we had a star and we
tried to put it in the thermal
equilibrium with its environment it
would do the same thing it would also
run away yeah negative specific heat
right exactly
negative specific heat is unstable but I
mean it doesn't mean black holes don't
exist it means in particular in the real
world they'll simply be absorbers which
will slowly absorb radiation eventually
the universe will expand and cool and
the temperature will go down below the
temperature of the black hole in which
case the black hole will start to give
off energy and it will evaporate okay so
let's let's talk about evaporation well
yeah they have temperature and because
they have temperature their black bodies
black bodies not in the sense that they
are completely dark but in the sense
that they give off thermal radiation I'm
going to go through the derivative or
just a very simple derivation of the
rate
at which black holes evaporate they were
rate at which they lose their energy but
I'm going to do it in units since I
really don't want to try to remember all
the places with C H bar G come in - this
will work in units where everything is
one and then we'll convert back the
sensible units now like I always like to
say if I were on a desert island and I
didn't have a physics book and I never
computer or anything else what units
would I work in they would be plunk
units because those are the only units
that I really remember things in it's
helpful to have some rough idea of how
big things are in plunk units and I'm
going to go through the derivation of
the luminosity of a black hole in plunk
units as I said the only reason is
everything is 1 so you never have to
worry where the constants go let's
remember what plunk units are they are
units in which the speed of light
Planck's constant and Newton's constant
are all equal to 1 C equals H bar equals
G equals 1 in those units the unit of
length the Planck length is about 10 to
the minus 35 meters the plunk time is
about 10 to the minus 42 43 seconds and
the plunk mass length time and mass
that's a complete set of units and the
plunk mass is about 10 to the minus
eighth kilograms the plunk mass is not a
particularly unusual mass 10 to the
minus 8 kilograms is about the mass of a
dust mote you can see it with a naked
eye so it's a it's a rather ordinary
mass a plunk time is incredibly short
and plunk length is incredibly small
all in fact the plunk time is nothing
but the time that it would take for a
light ray to cross the plunk distance so
they're not really independent if you
take the plunk distance and ask how long
it would take light to go across it it's
the plunk time all right let's work in
those units good now a black hole has
temperature because it has temperature
it radiates anything that has
temperature if in particular if it's put
into a vacuum we radiate blackbody
radiation blackbody radiation is simply
thermal radiation electromagnetic
radiation and incidentally it will also
radiate gravitational radiation but the
theories are absolutely parallel all
right um let's talk about the formula
for the luminosity of a warm body the
luminosity is the rate at which it loses
energy so we can write it as minus only
because the object is losing energy we
can write it as minus the rate of change
of the energy of the object some object
the EDT is the rate of change of its
energy it's losing energy so the e by DT
is negative and minus de by DT is
positive all right what is that first of
all it's proportional to the area of the
object when an object radiates it
radiates from the surface the bigger the
area the faster will radiate okay so the
area of the object appears here area and
this will become the area of the horizon
of the black hole
black holes radiate from the horizon and
then it depends on the temperature
obviously the hotter the temperature the
faster it radiates anybody know what
formula put the put here for the
temperature T to the fourth famous
formula Stefan Boltzmann formula
temperature to the fourth power you can
derive that from dimensional
consideration
is just a dimensional formula and what
about the coefficient which appears here
order of magnitude it's one because all
of the parameters are one so what else
could it be
right so in plunk units in plunk units
this is the rate at which the black hole
or anything else would lose energy now
energy is mass equals MC squared but C
is 1 so E is M here is M and we can
write this as the rate of change of the
loss of mass the rate of change of the
mass of the loss of mass per unit time
is the area times the temperature to the
fourth what is the area well the area is
proportional to the Schwarzschild radius
squared let's put that in there there's
some 4pi but by now we don't care about
those things 4pi but times are
Schwartzel squared and what about the
temperature they were we seem to have
lost the formula for the temperature go
back in your notes and see if you can
find the temperature well h plus 1 c is
but what's mg but what's mg R right let
me just let me remind you where the
temperature we discover found was H over
lambda times C this was the energy added
when we added one bit H and CL one and
so the temperature is just one over
lambda but lambda was supposed to be the
radius of the black hole so the
temperature is just 1 over the radius
the Schwarzschild radius all right so
temperature the fourth that's 1 over
radius to the fourth and this whole
thing just becomes all the radius to the
fourth or the rate of change of mass
with time is equal to 1 over R squared
oh but our resume isn't it yeah because
our is 2 mg in G is 1 & 2 is 1 right so
this is also just 1 over m squared ok
let's just remember wherever you see R
you can put em because they're
proportional to each other
M is energy this is the time rate of
change of energy and area 1 over R to
the fourth is temperature to the fourth
ok so that's all we did
that's what this formula says ok let's
sum multiply it by M squared minus M
squared DM what is M squared DM or the M
squared the M by DT M Squared the MDT
yeah apart from a factor of 3 M squared
times the MVP is just equal or what was
on the right hand side of the sir we hit
where there's the equation what happened
to the right here it's one right one
yeah all right so another way to write
this apart from a factor of three is the
time rate of change of the mass cubed of
the black hole is equal to 1 how long
does it take for the black hole to lose
all of its mass it has a uniform rate at
which it loses mass cubed so it's mass
cubed is diminishing one unit of it per
unit time how long does it take for all
that mass that you start with to
disappear right M cubed M cubed another
way you can write this is the change in
mass cubed divided by the change in time
is 1 and therefore the total time
that it takes to lose all of the mass is
just M cubed so M cubed that's how long
it takes
that's the evaporation time how long is
it
alright let's plug in let's plug in some
some numbers solar mass black hole helm
what's a solar mass 10 to the 30th the
kilograms so we have to look in plunk
units we did this in plunk units let's
do it in plunk units so the solar mass
is 10 to the 30th kilograms
how many plunk masses is that 10 to the
30th 10 to the 38th because the plunk
mass is 10 to the minus eighth kilograms
so 10 to the 38th plunk masses is the
mass of the Sun mass of the Sun that
symbol stands for Sun okay all right
what's the evaporation time
well it's M cubed so that's 10 to how
much what's 38 times 314 yeah so M cubed
is 10 to the hundred and fourteen but 10
to the hundred and fourteen what plunk
times plunk times times t plug a plunk
time is 10 to the minus 43 seconds so
how many seconds does this correspond to
10 to the 10 to the 71 10 to the 71
seconds how many years is that
one year is three times ten to the seven
seconds so divided by ten to the seventh
ten to the 60 ten to the sixty-four
years
what's the lot what's the present age of
the universe ten to the tenth years
right so this is 10 to the 54th universe
ages black holes evaporate very very
slowly the reason of course is they're
very very cold and you get T to the
fourth in them so even after the
universe cools to the point where the
black hole will evaporate it's still
evaporating very slowly okay all right
let's take a smaller black hole how
about a black hole of mountain mass
anybody have estimate from
well I see $10 and that one is the
hundred square cubic kilometers so TV
glamour is tended to what six meter
cubic meters times 110 to seven ten to
seven perfect insert work cubic meters I
think x times a pilgrim who says
densities three so therefore so it'd be
four times that ten times 48 you saying
are you saying
curcumin density is three times that of
water four times airport yeah okay how
many care to make meters 10 to 7 10 to
the seventh but you have to multiply by
10 to the three because the cubic meter
is about thousand kilograms no
yeah yeah so 10 to the tenth yes 10 to
10 10 to the let's say 10 to the 10 4
kilograms 10 to the 10th kilograms is
how many plunks 10 to the 18th 10 to the
18th the plum out 3 times 18 10 to the
54 that's 10 to the 54 clunk times and
now we take out 43 that was a 10 to the
11 seconds 10 to 11 seconds a lot
shorter
what's 10 to the 11 seconds 10 to the
7th 10 to the 4 years I I'm not not
terribly long that's still a pretty big
black hole a black hole of a few
kilograms
well a few kilograms the lifetime is
very short it just goes really fast bang
and you can work that out I don't want
to work it out now okay that's the
luminosity of a black hole but wouldn't
the sight of the kilogram and worth of
black hole be really small yeah are we
going to kill our good good the radius
is proportional to the mass right okay
the mass of the Sun is 10 to the 30th
and it corresponds to 1 or 1 or 2
kilometers so that means 1 kilogram
would be 10 to the minus 30 a--the
kilometers that's pretty small right
it's not as small as the Planck length
but it's pretty small yeah it's getting
there
right yeah well once once of course it
not all of these some of these some of
these would be no I think let's see um
yeah I think so yeah that's right well
only if they're ambient only if the
ambient temperature is cooler than they
are right all right so that's an
interesting question that what mass
would the black hole have a temperature
which is three degrees of background
radiation I'll leave that to you to
figure out work that out what's the size
of black hole size meaning radius and
mass of a black hole which which is
three degrees okay I think we've done
victory
yeah now what's the mechanism for these
photons coming out of it well before we
can answer that we have to answer what's
the mechanism for the entropy with in a
certain sense we're not so much guessing
most of this is based on very definite
calculation but it's the kind of them
it's the kind of theoretical work where
you put some principles together and you
say if you believe all the principles
then this is what has to be the
conclusion of it is that there are some
hidden small numerous degrees of freedom
that are not apparent in the standard
theory of black holes or on the standard
theory of gravity the understanding of
it and now is that the standard theory
of gravity is in a certain sense like
fluid dynamics fluid dynamics describes
a smooth flow of a uniform fluid I can
he'll also describe more turbulent flows
and so forth but it does not take into
account the atomic structure of fluids
there are of course circumstances where
fluids might the atomic structure might
become important but ordinary fluid flow
the equations of it are effective
equations which don't take into account
the microscopic structure you do put
entropy into the flow but you don't ask
where that entropy came from but just
the fact that there is entropy to a
fluid tells you there's a hidden
microscopic structure it's a clue it's a
hint that there's something there
besides just the smooth flow there's
something underlying it at smaller
distances there are hidden numerous
degrees of freedom so as things stand
today well as things stood some point I
think we understand a little more now
but we could say the theory that we've
talked about up till now is a strong
hint that there's more the theory of
gravity there's a micro structure to it
there's more to the theory of black hole
than just Einstein's theory there's
something smaller more numerous that
we're not keeping track of in ordinary
general relativity and in that sense
it's a hint it's a hint of something yet
to come we know a little more about it
by now but let's wait let's wait we'll
talk about what the hidden structures
might be in saying that the black hole
gives off energy
is that the same same block there's
enough information and so if the black
hole roll grows something in information
and then it shrinks again giving our
just going to get it back so you get
back all the same information that we
need to black hole purpose but you've
got to reconcile that with the figure
that we drew here that says things fall
through the horizon how the devil do
they get back out tell me about it when
you get it the conservation of
information is that a real fundamental
so that is the most fundamental it's so
fundamental that people tend to forget
about it
without it the rules all of the rules of
physics would make no sense for example
the rules that say that invariance is a
various kind time translation invariance
leads to energy conservation it does
only if you have the rule I'll give you
an example I'll give you an example
right now here's an eraser I slide the
array so along here now let's forget the
microscopic heat and everything else
let's suppose we lived in a world where
erasers really came to rest because they
satisfy the equations of motion that
made them come to rest rather than the
dirty physics of friction and so forth
but the real fundamental laws of motion
made erasers come to rest well first
thing is there would not be information
concept
raishin why because every year acer
comes the rest no matter how it started
so it simply forgets how it started
comes the rest and so it loses the
information about where it started
how about energy conservation there's no
energy to be conservative just comes to
rest
how about momentum conservation no
momentum conservation so what is what is
wrong with laws of physics which just
have erasers come to rest they violate
some of the basic principles of
classical mechanics and and quantum
mechanics but in the end what they're
violating is information conservation so
ideas of energy conservation momentum
conservation all the conservation or let
me say one more thing yeah come back
this eraser comes to rest that violates
momentum conservation does this violate
translation invariance the tabletop
imagine the tabletop or uniform and went
on forever and ever and the laws of
physics whether the eraser has come to
rest it doesn't violate translation
invariance so the statement that
momentum conservation follows from
translation invariance is apparently not
true here you need something else the
other thing that you need is information
conservation information conservation
plus invariance leads the momentum
conservation so yeah it it's not only
fundamental it's probably the most
single fundamental idea in physics well
no it's not the same um is it more
fundamental than causality no it's
probably at the same level though it
there one of these meta principles which
without which you couldn't even begin of
course that what do you mean by
causality exactly you mean that there
that
yeah yeah it's it's a similar kind of
principle that could be it in your
lecture classical mechanics so just
going to and you gave Hamilton's
formulation impossible okay and in that
I recall you saying a sawed-off teller
that the state space is maintains
uniform area yeah that's the principle
yeah okay in classical mechanics yes
that's called Lea villes theorem that's
right and information conservation in
classical mechanics is a statement that
the phase space volume doesn't change
that you can shrink the phase space
volume or anything like that
yeah in quantum mechanics it's called
unitarity and unitarity is a principle
that orthogonal states stay orthogonal
with time which means that distinctions
are always preserved and it's deeply
connected with energy conservation
yeah looking at this from an information
theoretic speculative you look at the
entropy functional it's it operational
probability not microstates no it
operates on probabilities for
microstates lot of other states
themselves the words it they when the
entropy is maximized wouldn't that
indicate the most problem it was a
probable problem distribution okay and
that's thermal equilibrium young thermal
equilibrium e4 information theory even
even if it's not formal it'll define the
the PDF okay that's that's that's a
definition going back to shadows paper
in 48 Decatur dealing with probabilities
of microstates and the entropy being
maximized will will indicate the
expected value of that the maximum value
prop of the PDF beautiful screen pop up
the problem the entropy equals a
probability distribution okay where my
closest is because it old it did it to
fit it defines one
the functional okay yes no the entropy
doesn't define a probability
distribution probability distribution
defines that's that's interesting
because in like information theory split
no entropy is minus the sum over all
configurations of the probability of the
I configure a ssin times the logarithm
or the I've configuration this is one
number and one number can't determine
peas peas determine s s is given in
terms of the peas but this is taking us
far afield this is taking us off yeah
uh-huh
okay for more please visit us at
stanford.edu